So we're on to our next section regarding Composition API
with Script Setup.
All right, so let's context set a bit here.
When we take a look at this user page,
you'll notice that, well, most of our component
is actually in Composition API, like minus the components
registration right here.
Everything else is Composition API.
And so Vue was certainly, when we were looking,
thinking about the developer experience of working
in Composition API, it was a bit like, well, OK,
this is cool, right?
We can break stuff up.
We can go ahead and write our JavaScript in a way
that's kind of more natural for us.
We can group it the way we want.
But then the fact that we have to constantly write our returns
gets a little bit tedious, especially when
you have a lot of things to return.
That's not something you have to manage in two different places.
You have to define what you're going to do,
then you're going to return it.
Couldn't Vue be a little bit smarter about this somehow?
And so this is where things like build tools are really great.
Because with Vue 3.2, we introduced a compiler optimization
where it allows us to actually fully buy into the Composition
API while saving us some code space and, more importantly,
allowing us to be more succinct and concise.
And so let me show you what I mean by that.
So let me go ahead and go over to the Playground
and let's go into the Pokedex.
All right.
So the Pokedex, similar to what we had earlier,
is basically mostly bought into the Composition API.
In fact, there's only a couple of things
we need to do to fully change it.
And so for now, let's see, computed.
In fact, this was a made up thing.
So we're going to go ahead and delete computed from here,
because we don't need this region name lowercase.
And then methods change region name, again,
was something we decided to do just to change things.
So we'll go ahead and migrate that.
Because what are methods?
Methods are JavaScript functions.
So const change region name equals function,
where we say region name.
And region name, in this particular case,
is a ref, which means we need to unpack it.
And it's going to be hoen.
Once we have that, we can return that to our template.
And then there we go.
And then we don't need to log any of this.
So now we should be back in a similar state
to what we had earlier when we had the user page.
OK.
So let me go ahead and actually check out branch 11 begin.
There we go.
And then we'll check out branch 11 exercise.
And let's commit this change real quick.
Feature, update, Pokedex to be almost fully composition API.
OK.
So what is script setup?
Well, script setup is exactly as it sounds,
in that what you do is you add an attribute
to your script block called setup.
And what that does is it tells you
this entire block is going to be composition API.
Like, no options will exist in here.
So what does that mean?
Well, first thing first, there's no more objects.
That's what options API is all about,
about defining this object.
So export default disappears.
Then we can save that.
But that's still going to break, which is totally fine,
because you know why?
We already know that it's in setup.
So line five, this async setup here,
also not necessary.
Delete.
Save.
Better.
But here's the other thing.
Because we're now in a compiler optimization,
meaning view can now do a lot more static analysis
and those sort of things, we don't even
need to return anything either.
And believe it or not, this block of code here, in fact,
let me just delete the console logs here,
this is whole thing just works.
It just sold me.
I was super skeptical until this moment.
Yeah, this is the mic drop moment for those who are thinking
about composition API.
This is, this makes a lot of people excited,
especially for those users who are heavier
on the JavaScript side.
Or more importantly, if you're even thinking about TypeScript,
composition API works with TypeScript like naturally,
in terms of annotating types and all that stuff.
We don't have time to talk about this today,
but there's a View3 and TypeScript workshop that just
actually released recently.
So if you want to check that out to learn more
about how that might work together,
you can totally check that out.
But there you go.
This is how you get a component to fully opt
into composition API while not having to worry
about any of the eight.
One of the things actually that you might be thinking though
is that we had an async earlier on our setup.
But when you're in the script setup,
basically view, hoist, and does all the async stuff for you
so that you don't have to manually assign it here.
It'll automatically detect the async stuff
and do what it needs to do.
And so just like that, we now have a component that's fully
opted into composition API.
No options anywhere.
The only thing I will add is because this probably
wouldn't be the most intuitive, is that let's say we wanted
to add our base button inside of this layout.
All we do is you do base button.
We import it into this base button.
And believe it or not, just by importing it,
you've already registered it.
So I can come down in here now and just go base button like that.
You can see there's our base button.
So a little bit of show and tell.
Does anyone have any questions about what they've seen so far?
I have to imagine that in practice,
this really forces you to make concise components
because it's going to be a mess if your component doesn't.
And you bring up an excellent point.
So as we can see here, right now the code
is fairly short, easy to follow.
But you can imagine it's very easy for a team
to get carried away with this.
And spaghetti code can become very problematic very quickly.
Again, one of the things I want to emphasize
is that there are trade-offs when you go the options route
versus the composition API route.
And understanding those trade-offs
are, if we think about it, are what make us experience
as engineers.
And so knowing that, you just have
to realize that composition API means there's
flexibility and freedom.
And so your team has to then design the conventions it's
going to use in order to make sure that your code is still
maintainable and readable.
As much as options API was a little bit rigid,
as far as telling you where to put stuff,
it did mean everyone knew where everything was at any point.
And anyone could basically jump in.
But here, this is just the beginning.
Because what we're going to do next
after you all practice doing this yourselves
is we're going to talk about how you can extract these
into modules that can then be basically
tossed around different components.
There is one more thing I need to cover
before we cover the exercise.
We've done all this stuff regarding doing functionality,
data, computed, and we've talked about components.
We did not talk about props.
We did not talk about mitts.
So you remember, if you look at our user
card that I had earlier, we see that in the options,
it's very easy.
You just have the props.
You have your mitts.
You just define it as you see fit.
It's actually not that much harder
when it comes to composition API.
It's just, what do you think you need?
You need a helper function.
And so they are aptly named define props.
And they are define emits.
These are the two helper methods that you need to know about.
And so the way it works is basically,
if this Pokedex wanted to say take a region of props,
sorry, a region of conto, for example, of which region
it was looking for, you would say define props
is a function that takes an object where we can then
can say the region is going to be of type string.
And I can say the default is going to be conto, for example.
As you can see, the syntax is actually very similar to what
we learned already.
The main difference being that, one,
is being called by a function.
But the second part, which is actually really important,
is that if you wanted to actually use the prop
in your computation, say, for instance,
inside of this computed, we wanted to actually say
we want it to be uppercase, and we want to add the prop to it,
too.
How do we do that?
Well, define props as it stands right here.
It's just a function that's being initiated.
What we need to do then, because it's vanilla JavaScript,
is say const props.
Or to be honest, you can name it whatever you want.
It's JavaScript.
But I would recommend just naming it props.
Because then, you can say props.region.
And then when you do that, you can see at least,
oh, it looks like the default is giving me some problems.
So I'm going to ignore that for now.
But we can see here, if I go to app.view,
where is a wrong app.view?
App.view in the playground, give it a region.
Let's just switch it up to ho in this time.
There we go.
I'll just figure out what the default thing is later.
But at the bare minimum, you can see
that's how you define props.
And then similarly, if you're doing emit,
you basically const emit, define the emit.
And then here, same thing we can say, change region,
for example.
And then everything still works exactly as we
learned in this workshop.
How influx is this API?
Define props and define emits is?
I mean, the whole whole section you just showed.
Got it.
OK, so the question here is around how stable the script
setup is.
It's fully stable at this point, production ready.
Ever since 3.2, so that's the big caveat here.
If you're using anything less than view 3.2,
you won't have script setup.
The compiler optimizations aren't there.
But going forward, honestly, I have seen a lot of code bases.
A lot of people just opt into this fully from the get go.
So yeah, consider it stable on that end.
For things like define props, define emits,
they're still playing around a little bit sometimes
with how they can optimize the DX of like, as you saw,
default was acting a little bit funky.
I don't have to look into that why.
But those are things that are still kind of being refined.
But if you can be guaranteed of anything,
it's that view tried to do its best
to be progressive about how it makes its changes,
so that as long as it's not marked as experimental,
you can count on your stuff working in production.
And then sure, we might introduce another syntax
that would make it even easier for you,
just like we saw with script setup.
Because we got feedback on Composition API, right?
People liked it, kind of verbose,
but people had their feelings about it.
And when we saw, I think, inspired by things
like Svelte was doing with compiler optimizations,
we said, why not?
These are things that we can also do for our users.
And so script setup, I believe, don't quote me on this,
but I believe was also inspired from what we saw with Svelte.
Cool.
So actually, we're not calling emits right now,
so I'm just gonna, actually I can just make
an example for people right in here.
Do, do, do, do.
We could say, emits.
What does it emit?
It emits the change region.
That's your example right there.
Okay, cool.